<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "http://thor-f5.er.usgs.gov/ngtoc/metadata/fgdc-std-001-1998.dtd"[]>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, National Geospatial Technical Operations Center</origin>
        <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
        <title>USGS Topo Map Vector Data (Vector) 70426 Howard, South Dakota 20180210 for 7.5 x 7.5 minute Shapefile</title>
        <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>ftp://rockyftp.cr.usgs.gov/vdelivery/Datasets/Staged/TopoMapVector/SD/Shape/VECTOR_Howard_SD_7_5_Min_Shape.zip</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Layers of geospatial data include contours, boundaries, land cover, hydrography, roads, transportation, geographic names, structures,
        and other selected map features.</abstract>
      <purpose>This dataset depicts geographic features on the surface of the earth. It is a general purpose dataset for users who are not GIS
        experts. The geospatial data in this dataset are from selected National Map data holdings and other government sources.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20111109</begdate>
          <enddate>20170925</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>publication date</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Irregular</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-97.6249999999999</westbc>
        <eastbc>-97.4999999999999</eastbc>
        <northbc>44.1250000000001</northbc>
        <southbc>44.0000000000001</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>contours</themekey>
        <themekey>transportation</themekey>
        <themekey>structures</themekey>
        <themekey>geographic names</themekey>
        <themekey>hydrography</themekey>
        <themekey>boundary</themekey>
        <themekey>Public Land Survey System</themekey>
        <themekey>woodland</themekey>
        <themekey>Combined Vector</themekey>
        <themekey>7.5 x 7.5 minute</themekey>
        <themekey>Shapefile</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>US</placekey>
        <placekey>United States</placekey>
        <placekey>SD</placekey>
        <placekey>South Dakota</placekey>
        <placekey>MinerCounty</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None. However, users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since this data set was collected and that some parts of
      this data may no longer represent actual surface conditions. Users should not use this data for critical applications without a full awareness
      of its limitations. Acknowledgment of the U.S. Geological Survey would be appreciated for products derived from these data.</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>ftp://rockyftp.cr.usgs.gov/vdelivery/Datasets/Staged/TopoMapVector/SD/Shape/VECTOR_Howard_SD_7_5_Min_Shape.jpg</browsen>
      <browsed>Thumbnail JPG image</browsed>
      <browset>JPEG</browset>
    </browse>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Content is derived from USGS national geospatial databases. The data is owned and hosted by the USGS, but does not preclude using data
        sources owned and hosted by other organizations, provided that these sources have been approved by the USGS data program.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>This product is a layered set of data. This design is based on use of specific commercial software systems therefore any changes to the
      software specifications and dependencies will be followed by the USGS and codified in the product standard.</logic>
    <complete>Each layer is extracted from the USGS national geospatial databases.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>There is a diversity of national data sources in this product. Although the data accuracy varies, the data generally have high
          enough horizontal accuracy to support NMAS and mapping at 1:24,000 scale. NMAS horizontal accuracy requires that at least 90 percent of
          well-defined points tested are within 0.02 inch of the true position.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>Contours are generated from the National Elevation Dataset (NED). The most recently published figure of overall absolute vertical
          accuracy of the NED within the conterminous US, expressed as the root mean square error (RMSE) of 25,310 reference points is 1.55 meters.
          However, the vertical accuracy actually varies significantly across the US because of differences in source quality, terrain relief, land
          cover, and other factors. Details of this analysis are published in "Accuracy Assessment of the U.S. Geological Survey National Elevation
          Dataset, and Comparison with Other Large-Area Elevation Datasets-SRTM and ASTER: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 2014-1008,"
          http://pubs.usgs.gov/2014.1008/ .</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, National Geospatial Technical Operations Center - National Elevation Dataset is a component of a
              comprehensive base geospatial data model.</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Hypsography</title>
            <geoform>Vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit> This contour feature class was generated from the 1/3 arc-second version of the 3D Elevation Program. The intended viewing
              scale for these features is 1:24,000. The contours are derived from a filtered elevation raster to achieve smoother arcs. In some areas,
              the 3DEP data may be modified by the National Hydrography Dataset (NHD) flow lines and water bodies to facilitate improved integration
              between the hypsography and hydrography on USGS map products. These contours were generated primarily for use as a layer in GeoPDFs
              created in the digital mapping program. The raster data source of contours is the 3D Elevation Program 1/3 arc-second layer. Secondary
              datasets include the high resolution flow lines, water bodies, and areas from the National Hydrography Dataset (NHD). The NHD layers are
              used in hydro-enforcement of the DEM prior to contour generation. The goals of the hydro-enforcement are to prevent contour lines from
              extending over the surface of water bodies and to align the contour reentrants with the NHD single- line streams. The 3DEP raster cells
              are converted to points. Those points, along with the NHD flow lines are input into an interpolation tool to create a new surface. The
              NHD water bodies and areas are preprocessed to attach the minimum and maximum elevation to each polygon. From these precalculated
              values, an appropriate value is calculated by which to raise the elevation cells under the NHD polygons. The NHD polygons are then
              converted into rasters, which in turn will be used to generate a mosaic that includes the new raster surface. The mosaic is filtered to
              provide smoother contour lines. Contours are generated and depression and index contours are identified. There is no guarantee or
              warranty concerning the accuracy of the data. Users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since these data were
              collected and generated and that some parts of these data may no longer represent actual surface conditions. Hydro-enforcement and
              generalization can also significantly alter the spatial characteristics of the contours. Users should not use these data for critical
              applications without a full awareness of its limitations. </othercit>
            <onlink>http://ned.usgs.gov/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate />
              <enddate />
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Hypsography</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Contours</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>International Boundary Commission</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>U.S.-Canada National Boundary</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The boundary is a digital representation of the International boundary between the United States and Canada as per the Treaty of
              1908. It has been generated from a combination of recent surveys and datum conversions. It is intended for general mapping purposes
              only. The boundary dataset is composed of 29 segments that correspond to the original 256 boundary maps. Attributes of each segment
              define the scale in which the line in that area may be accurately depicted. It is produced for mapping purposes only and not intended to
              illustrate the boundary beyond the limits of the scale for any given segment</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.internationalboundarycommission.org/</onlink>
            <onlink>http://www.internationalboundarycommission.org/index-eng.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2006</begdate>
              <enddate>2006</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>U.S. / Canada International Boundary</srccitea>
        <srccontr>International Boundary between Canada and the United States</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin> U.S. Geological Survey, U.S. Department of Agriculture, and the Instituto Nacional de Estadistica y Geografia of Mexico. </origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>U.S.-Mexico National Boundary</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The international boundary between Mexico and the United States, defined as a joint venture between the U.S. Department of
              Agriculture (USDA) and the Instituto Nacional de Estadistica y Geografia of Mexico (INEGI), resulted in an unofficial United
              States-Mexico boundary dataset that was further enhanced by the U.S. Geological Survey's Border Environmental Health Initiative (BEHI).
              With the data frame scale set to 1:5,000 in ArcMap, the center of the Rio Grande/Rio Bravo was digitized using the NAIP 2004 Imagery. In
              areas with dense stands of salt cedar (bounding box = UL -104.714 30.038, UR -104.664 30.037, LR -104.666 29.933, LL -104.717 29.934;
              NAD83), the center of the channel was difficult, and sometimes impossible, to easily determine. To determine the location of the
              boundary, the GIS analyst compared the location of the line in the INEGI 1:250K Limite feature class with the NAIP 2004 Imagery and
              adjusted the boundary to the image, thus, the delineation of the international boundary is less certain in these areas. The remaining
              part of the border was extracted from the INEGI 1:250K Limite feature class and appended to the line feature class created along the Rio
              Grande/Rio Bravo. The U.S. Geological Survey reviewed the original USDA data against 2007 NAIP imagery and further edited 9 line
              segments in the Rio Grande areas to conform to National Map Accuracy Standards.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://borderhealth.cr.usgs.gov/projectindex.html</onlink>
            <onlink>http://extract.cr.usgs.gov/BorderHealth/Boundaries/Int_Boundary/International_Boundary_Shapefile.zip</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>1972</begdate>
              <enddate>2006</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>U.S. / Mexico International Boundary</srccitea>
        <srccontr>International Boundary between Mexico and the United States</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin> U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) Forest Service - Washington Office Automated Lands Program (ALP). </origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>USDA Forest Service Boundary</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The forest service boundaries defined by the USDA Forest Service encompassing the National Forest System (NFS) lands within the
              original proclaimed National Forests, along with lands added to the NFS which have taken on the status of 'reserved from the public
              domain' under the General Exchange Act. The following area types are included: National Forest, Experimental Area, Experimental Forest,
              Experimental Range, Land Utilization Project, National Grassland, Purchase Unit, and Special Management Area. The nationwide Proclaimed
              Forest dataset was created by the USDA Forest Service, Washington Office Automated Lands Program (ALP) staff from collected source data
              created by the Regional Offices. Only maps in USDA Forest Service areas will contain USDA Forest boundaries.</othercit>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2009</begdate>
              <enddate>2009</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>USDA Forest Service Boundaries</srccitea>
        <srccontr>National Forest Service Boundaries</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Office of the Deputy Under Secretary of Defense for Installations and Environment, Business Enterprise Integration
              Directorate</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>U.S. Military Installations, Ranges, and Training Areas</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>This dataset depicts the authoritative boundaries of the most commonly known Department of Defense (DoD) sites, installations,
              ranges, and training areas in the United States and Territories. These sites encompass land which is federally owned or otherwise
              managed. This dataset was compiled by the Defense Installation Spatial Data Infrastructure (DISDI) Program. This dataset represents the
              baseline for georeferenced boundaries of sites selected from the 2010 Base Structure Report. The boundary locations are intended for
              planning purposes only and do not represent the legal or surveyed land parcel boundaries. This list does not necessarily represent a
              comprehensive collection of all DoD facilities, and only those in the fifty United States and US Territories were considered for
              inclusion. Maps produced at a scale of 1:50,000 or larger which otherwise comply with National Map Accuracy Standards will remain
              compliant if this data is incorporated. Although these data have been provided by the DoD components, no warranty expressed or implied
              is made regarding the utility of the data on any other system, in derived products or data alterations, nor shall the act of
              distribution constitute such warranty.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.acq.osd.mil/ie/index.shtml</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>50000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2011</begdate>
              <enddate>2011</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>U.S. Department of Defense Military Installations</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Boundary lines, installation names</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Census Bureau</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>State and Equivalent Boundary</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The Census Bureau collects boundaries from state and county governments through the Boundary and Annexation Survey, and
              publishes the results as TIGER files. The USGS uses the TIGER data without editing or alteration.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.census.gov/geo/maps-data/data/tiger.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2013</begdate>
              <enddate>2014</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>State Boundaries</srccitea>
        <srccontr>State and Equivalent Boundary</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Census Bureau</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>County and Equivalent Boundary</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The Census Bureau collects boundaries from state and county governments through the Boundary and Annexation Survey (BAS), and
              publishes the results as TIGER files. The USGS uses the TIGER data without editing or alteration for US Topo.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.census.gov/geo/www/tiger/index.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2013</begdate>
              <enddate>2014</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>County Boundaries</srccitea>
        <srccontr>County and Equivalent Boundary</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Census Bureau</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Incorporated Places Boundary</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The boundaries of most incorporated places are as of January 1, 2013, as reported through the Census Bureau's Boundary and
              Annexation Survey. Limited updates that occurred after January 1, 2013, such as newly incorporated places, are also included. The
              boundaries of all Census Designated Places (CDP) were delineated as part of the Census Bureau's Participant Statistical Areas Program
              (PSAP) for the 2010 Census. The USGS uses the TIGER data without editing or alteration.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.census.gov/geo/www/tiger/index.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2013</begdate>
              <enddate>2014</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Incorporated Places Boundaries</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Incorporated Places Boundaries</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Census Bureau</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Jurisdictional Boundary</title>
            <othercit>The 115th Congress is seated from January 2017 to 2019. The TIGER/Line shapefiles for the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico, and
              the Island Areas (American Samoa, Guam, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, and the U.S. Virgin Islands) each contain a
              single record for the non-voting delegate district in these areas. The boundaries of all other congressional districts are provided to
              the Census Bureau through the Redistricting Data Program (RDP). The USGS uses the TIGER data without editing or alteration for US
              Topo.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.census.gov/geo/maps-data/data/tiger.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2016</begdate>
              <enddate>2016</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Jurisdictional Boundaries</srccitea>
        <srccontr>115th Congressional Districts Boundaries</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Census Bureau</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Minor Civil Divisions Boundary</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The boundaries of most legal Minor Civil Divisions (MCD) are as of January 1, 2013, as reported through the Census Bureau's
              Boundary and Annexation Survey. The boundaries of all Census Designated Places (CDP)are those as reported as part of the Census Bureau's
              Participant Statistical Areas Program (PSAP) for the 2010 Census. The USGS uses the TIGER data without editing or alteration.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.census.gov/geo/www/tiger/index.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2013</begdate>
              <enddate>2014</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Minor Civil Divisions Boundaries</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Minor Civil Divisions Boundaries</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Census Bureau</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Native American Area Boundary</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The Native American Area boundaries are as of January 1, 2013 as reported through Census Bureau's Boundary and Annexation
              Survey. The USGS dataset is a combination of two Census Bureau files. It includes the American Indian/Alaska Native/Native Hawaiian
              Areas National (AIANNH) National TIGER/Line shapefile, including the following legal entities: federally recognized American Indian
              reservations and off-reservation trust land areas, state-recognized American Indian reservations, and Hawaiian home lands. Also included
              is the Alaska Native Regional Corporation (ANRC) State-based TIGER/Line shapefile containing a record of the 12 Alaska Native Regional
              Corporations used to conduct both the for-profit and non-profit affairs of Alaska Natives within a defined region of Alaska. The USGS
              uses the TIGER data without editing or alteration.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.census.gov/geo/www/tiger/index.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2013</begdate>
              <enddate>2014</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Native American Area Boundaries</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Native American Area Boundaries</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>National Park Service - Land Resources Division</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>National Park Service Boundary</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>This dataset depicts National Park Service unit boundaries for display and general analysis purposes. The USGS converted areas
              of generally 3 acres or less to point features to facilitate cartographic display on the US Topo digital map product. See Source URL for
              link to complete dataset. This data set is complete but subject to continual updates to reflect boundary amendments, legislation, and
              acquisitions, and improved processing techniques. The data is being regularly updated with verified boundaries from NPS Land Resources
              Division. The data is intended for use as a tool for display and general GIS analysis purposes only. It is in no way intended for
              engineering or legal purposes. The data accuracy is checked against best available sources which may be dated. NPS assumes no liability
              for use of this data. Boundaries from the Land Resources Division have separate polygons for each type of unit. For example Denali
              National Park and Denali National Preserve are separate individual polygons.</othercit>
            <onlink>https://irma.nps.gov/App/Portal</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2002</begdate>
              <enddate>2014</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>National Park Service Boundary</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Current Administrative Boundaries of the National Park System Units</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Census Bureau</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Unincorporated Places Boundary</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The boundaries of most unincorporated places in this shapefile are as of January 1, 2013, as reported through the Census
              Bureau's Boundary and Annexation Survey (BAS). Limited updates that occurred after January 1, 2013, such as newly unincorporated places,
              are also included. The boundaries of all Census Designated Places (CDPs) were delineated as part of the Census Bureau's Participant
              Statistical Areas Program (PSAP) for the 2010 Census. The USGS uses the TIGER data without editing or alteration.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.census.gov/geo/www/tiger/index.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2013</begdate>
              <enddate>2014</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Unincorporated Places Boundaries</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Unincorporated Places Boundaries</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Department of Interior, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>US Fish and Wildlife Service</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>This data set depicts simplified boundaries of lands administered by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service including National
              Wildlife Refuges, National Fish Hatcheries, FWS administrative sites, and other conservation areas. The Alaska National Wildlife Refuge
              Boundaries data set depicts the legislative boundary of the 16 National Wildlife Refuges in Alaska at a source scale of 1:63,360. The
              dataset was created by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Region 7, Division of Realty and Natural Resources. The USGS substituted the
              Alaska National Wildlife Refuge boundaries for the USFWS Simplified Wildlife Refuge Boundaries in Alaska for cartographic purposes. The
              USFWS Simplified Wildlife Refuge Boundaries are simplified from the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service Real Estate Interest data layer
              containing polygons representing tracts of land (parcels) in which the Service has a property or management interest. These interests
              include full land ownership, secondary interests in property primarily managed and reported by other federal agencies, leased property,
              property managed by agreement with other parties, and, within National Wildlife Refuges, property governed by conservation easements. A
              conservation easement is a permanent, legally enforceable land preservation agreement between a landowner and a government agency that
              restricts real estate, commercial and industrial development of the land, which remains private property. Inholdings of private property
              within Refuge areas not covered by conservation easements are excluded from these boundaries. The Hawaiian Islands National Wildlife
              Refuge and Waterfowl production area easements acquired through the small wetlands program have been omitted. Interior boundaries
              between parcels were dissolved to produce a single set of simplified external boundaries for each feature. These are resource grade
              mapping representations of the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service boundaries. For legal descriptions of the land represented here contact
              the USFWS Realty Office. This map layer was compiled by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service. The Alaska National Wildlife Refuges dataset
              was derived from the following digital sources and legal documents: 1) Federal Register, Vol. 48, No. 38 Thursday, February 24, 1983
              Notices Pages 7890-8029. 2) USGS 1:250,000 scale Alaska Boundary Series maps entitled: Alaska National Interest Lands Conservation Act
              December 2, 1980 P.L. 96-487 3) Various legal documents such as survey plats, legal metes and bounds descriptions, Deeds, and Titles. 4)
              USGS 1:63,360 scale revised hydrography Digital Line Graphs depicting ground conditions from 1955 to 1986. Although these Fish and
              Wildlife boundaries represent lands administered by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, not all areas are open to the public. Some
              fragile habitats need to be protected from human traffic, some management areas are closed, and the terms of some conservation easements
              preclude public access. The public is urged to contact specific Refuges or other conservation areas before visiting.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.fws.gov/GIS/data/CadastralDB/FWS_Simplified_Boundaries.zip</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>1950</begdate>
              <enddate>2014</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>U. S. Fish and Wildlife Service Boundary</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Boundary polygons and names</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Dept. of Interior, Bureau of Land Management, Division of Support Services, Branch of Information Resource
              Management</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Public Land Survey System</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The PLSS information is for general reference purposes only, and should not be used to determine legal boundaries or land
              ownership. The Bureau of Land Management (BLM) is the authoritative source for PLSS information at the federal level, and the US Topo
              representation is derived from BLM GIS data files called Cadastral National Spatial Data Infrastructure or CadNSDI. The management of
              these data is not completely uniform throughout the country. Although this metadata record is included with all maps, PLSS is currently
              shown on US Topo Maps for only a few states. PLSS will be added to US Topo maps in more states in coming years as BLM authorized CadNSDI
              format is made available. The three layers USGS stores from PLSS are the Township, First Division and Special Surveys. Metadata for BLM
              PLSS data is at http://www.geocommunicator.gov/GeoComm/metadata/index.htm#PLSS, though this URL may change in the near future. Alternate
              sources of PLSS data will continued to be served mainly in western states where BLM is the data steward or the data is from a trusted
              source. Notes on individual states follow,----Alaska PLSS consists of protracted (computed, not surveyed) data only. For more
              information see http://sdms.ak.blm.gov/sdms/data_protracted_grid_gis.html----Ohio was the original PLSS state in the early 1800s, and
              the land network there is unusually complex. The source data include four first-division parcel types. These are all shown on US Topo
              maps, and are labeled according to BLM's attribution, with a leading letter followed by either a number or more letters. The meanings of
              the leading letters are S=Section, F=Fractional Section, L=Lot, Q=Quarter Township.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://sdms.ak.blm.gov/sdms/data_protracted_grid_gis.html</onlink>
            <onlink>http://www.geocommunicator.gov/GeoComm/lsis_home/home/index.htm</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2008</begdate>
              <enddate>2015</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Public Land Survey System - BLM</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Townships and ranges, sections</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Department of Veterans Affairs, National Cemetery Administration and U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>NCA National Cemeteries</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>This dataset represents boundaries of National cemeteries administered by the U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs, National
              Cemetery Administration. This layer may also contain a small number of boundaries for those managed by the Department of the Army. This
              data is subject to change as other national cemetery areas are authorized. This dataset is intended for general mapping and reference
              purposes only.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://nationalmap.gov/boundaries.html/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2013</begdate>
              <enddate>2014</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>National Cemetery Boundary</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Name, general location information from NCA, Boundaries from parcel and other mapping datasets.</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, National Geospatial Technical Operations Center</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Geographic Names Information System (GNIS)</title>
            <geoform>Vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The Geographic Names Information System (GNIS) is the Federal and national standard for geographic nomenclature. The U.S.
              Geological Survey developed the GNIS in support of the U.S. Board on Geographic Names as the official repository of domestic geographic
              names data, the official vehicle for geographic names use by all departments of the Federal Government, and the source for applying
              geographic names to Federal electronic and printed products.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://geonames.usgs.gov/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2012</begdate>
              <enddate>2012</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Geographic Names</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Geographic feature names</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, National Geospatial Technical Operations Center</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Land Cover - Woodland</title>
            <geoform>Vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The Woodland Tint is a derivative land cover product created using several national map layers: three National Land Cover
              Database (NLCD) 2001 raster layers (Tree Canopy, Imperviousness, and Land Cover); and two vector layers (National Hydrography Dataset
              and Transportation). The process begins with masking the NLCD 2001 Canopy Data with NLCD 2001 Imperviousness V1 (values from 1-100), and
              Land Cover V1 (value 11 = Open Water). The resulting raster data with canopy values of 20 and greater are converted to woodland vector
              polygons and smoothed via the Paek Algorithm. The woodland polygons are masked with buffered Transportation (Roads, Airport Runways, and
              Railroads) and Hydrography (NHD Areas excluding Inundation Area and NHD Waterbodies excluding Swamp/Marsh). The resulting polygons are
              checked for scale appropriate size (minimum size of one acre), and the small woodland polygons as well as small clearings within the
              woodland polygons are deleted.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://nationalmap.usgs.gov</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2001</begdate>
              <enddate>2012</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Land Cover - Woodland</srccitea>
        <srccontr>National Landcover Dataset; National Hydrography Dataset; National Transportation Dataset</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey in cooperation with U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, USDA Forest Service, and other Federal, State and
              local partners. National Hydrography Dataset is a component of a comprehensive base geospatial data model.</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Hydrography</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The National Hydrography Dataset (NHD) is a feature-based database that interconnects and uniquely identifies the stream
              segments or reaches that make up the nation's surface water drainage system. The high-resolution NHD was originally created using
              1:24,000-scale data. State and Local Stewards are improving the data by incorporating local updates based on more current and more
              accurate source data. Water features in the real world are relatively dynamic and the differences at the time of data collection mean
              that water features may not register exactly to other layers. The hydrographic feature names contained in and displayed by the NHD are
              extracted and validated from the Geographic Names Information System (GNIS). Spatial objects may be filtered or generalized to achieve a
              1:24,000-scale representation.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://nhd.usgs.gov/</onlink>
            <onlink>http://nhd.usgs.gov/gnis.html</onlink>
            <onlink>http://nhdgeo.usgs.gov/metadata/nhd_high.htm</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>20100820</begdate>
              <enddate>20100820</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Hydrography</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Hydrography features and feature names</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Global Land Ice Measurements from Space initiative (GLIMS)</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Gaging Stations</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>This dataset, termed "GAGES II", an acronym for Geospatial Attributes of Gages for Evaluating Streamflow, version II, provides
              geospatial data and classifications for 9,322 stream gages maintained by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). It is an update to the
              original GAGES in 2010. The GAGES II dataset consists of gages which have had either 20+ complete years (not necessarily continuous) of
              discharge record since 1950, or are currently active, as of water year 2009, and whose watersheds lie within the United States,
              including Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico. Only active stations, as identified by the GAGES II dataset, are symbolized.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://water.usgs.gov/lookup/getspatial?gagesII_Sept2011</onlink>
            <onlink>http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/metadata/usgswrd/XML/gagesII_Sept2011.xml</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate />
              <enddate />
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Hydrography - Gaging Stations</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Hydrography features and gaging stations</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>State and Federal Partners, updates from USGS' The National Map Corps volunteers </origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Fire Stations</title>
            <geoform>Vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>Any location where fire fighters are stationed or based out of, or where equipment that such personnel use in carrying out their
              jobs is stored for ready use. Fire Departments which are Mobile Units and not having a permanent location, are included, in which case
              their location has been depicted at the city/town hall or at the center of their service area if a city/town hall does not exist. This
              dataset includes those locations primarily engaged in forest or grasslands fire fighting, including fire lookout towers if the towers
              are in current use for fire protection purposes. This dataset includes both private and governmental entities. Locations that serve only
              administrative function are excluded. Locations serving both administrative and operational functions are included.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://nationalmap.usgs.gov</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>None</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>20060101</begdate>
              <enddate>20120101</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Structures - Fire Stations</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Geographic features and feature names</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin> State and Federal Partners, updates from USGS' The National Map Corps volunteers</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Law Enforcement</title>
            <geoform>Vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>Included are locations where sworn officers of a law enforcement agency are regularly based or stationed. This dataset includes
              local police, county sheriff's offices, state police or highway patrol locations. Most federal law enforcement agency locations are not
              included.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://nationalmap.usgs.gov</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>None</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>20051019</begdate>
              <enddate>20150203</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Structures - Law Enforcement</srccitea>
        <srccontr> Geographic features and feature names</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin> State and Federal Partners, updates from USGS' The National Map Corps volunteers</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Prisons/Correctional Facility</title>
            <geoform>Vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>Includes both private and government medium and high security prisons and correctional institutions. Low and minimum security
              institutions such as local jails, prison camps, correctional farms or work farms, detention and treatment centers are generally
              excluded.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://nationalmap.usgs.gov</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>None</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>20070803</begdate>
              <enddate>20150203</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Structures - Prisons/Correctional Facility</srccitea>
        <srccontr> Geographic features and feature names</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>State and Federal Partners, updates from USGS' The National Map Corps volunteers </origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Schools</title>
            <geoform>Vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The schools within this dataset are composed of Public elementary and secondary education in the US as defined and tracked by
              the National Center for Education Statistics (NCES), Common Core Dataset (CCD). Private schools in this dataset are composed of Private
              elementary and secondary education in the US as defined by the Private School Survey, NCES. The colleges and Universities are composed
              of postsecondary education facilities as defined by the Integrated Post Secondary Education System (IPEDS), NCES. Included are Doctoral
              and Research Universities, Masters Colleges and Universities, Baccalaureate Colleges, Associates Colleges, Theological seminaries,
              Medical schools and other health care professions, schools of engineering and technology, business and management, art, music, design,
              Law schools, Teachers colleges, Tribal colleges and other specialized institutions.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://nationalmap.usgs.gov</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>None</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>20080101</begdate>
              <enddate>20080101</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Structures - Schools</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Geographic features and feature names</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>State and Federal Partners, updates from USGS' The National Map Corps volunteers </origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Hospitals</title>
            <geoform>Vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>Includes general medical and surgical hospitals, psychiatric, substance abuse and specialty hospitals such as Children's
              hospitals, cancer, maternity and rehabilitation hospitals. Other types of hospitals are included if represented in data sets provided by
              various partners for this compilation. Hospitals operated by the US Department of Veterans Affairs are included. Nursing homes, long
              term care facilities and Urgent Care facilities are generally excluded. Locations that are administrative offices only are excluded from
              the dataset.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://nationalmap.usgs.gov</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>None</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>20060101</begdate>
              <enddate>20110101</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Structures - Hospitals</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Geographic features and feature names</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>State government websites</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>State Capitol buildings</title>
            <geoform>Vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>Includes the official State Capitol buildings for the U.S. states and territories</othercit>
            <onlink>http://nationalmap.usgs.gov</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>None</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2014</begdate>
              <enddate>2014</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Structures - State Capitol building</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Geographic features and feature names</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Transportation, Railroads</title>
            <geoform>Vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>Railroads are derived from an unpublished data set provided to USGS by Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL) Geographic
              Information Science and Technology Group (GIST). Following is an excerpt from the GIST description of the data set; the original data
              contain attributes not used by US Topo: The rail lines layer represents the freight lines of the nation's railroad system. The data set
              covers all 50 states and the District of Columbia, as well as territories and possessions of the United States. No rail lines exist in
              American Samoa, Guam, Northern Mariana Islands, and the Virgin Islands of the US. Phase 1 of this product is a completed deliverable.
              This phase involved adding and validating network attribute data including railroad ownership, trackage and haulage rights, operational
              status, operating subdivisions, signaling systems, track class and traffic density. Phase 2 adjusted the topological alignment of the
              track using the best available remote sensing imagery. Information originally based on the Department of Transportation (DOT) Federal
              Railroad Administration (FRA) 1:100K rail network. The data have been updated by Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL) Geographic
              Information Science and Technology Group (GIST).</othercit>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2014</begdate>
              <enddate>2014</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Railroads - Oak Ridge National Laboratory</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Main track centerlines</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Federal Aviation Administration</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Airports</title>
            <geoform>Vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>Runway outlines are for Federal Aviation Administration (FAA)-recognized public and private airports in the United States. The
              FAA runway coordinates, FAA_RunwayID, and Airport Location Codes were used by the USGS to digitize runway outlines on recent NAIP
              orthoimagery. The digitized data were inspected for accuracy and completeness then loaded into the USGS national transportation
              database.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.faa.gov</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2011</begdate>
              <enddate>2012</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Transportation - Airports</srccitea>
        <srccontr>runways</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Various government agencies and volunteer organizations</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Recreational Trails</title>
            <geoform>Vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The first recreational trails were added to US Topo maps in 2013. The data for trails come from a variety of sources. Accuracy
              and currency is the responsibility of the data owner; USGS evaluates the authoritativeness of the source but does not independently
              verify data accuracy. Trails are not complete, and will not be complete for the foreseeable future. Trails will be added as data become
              available from land management agencies and other authoritative sources. All recreational trails information presented on US Topo maps
              is public domain, though the original source data is not necessarily public domain. This metadata section documents all data sources for
              all maps, not this specific map. Trails listed here are not guaranteed to be present on all relevant maps, due to schedule differences
              between data delivery and US Topo production schedules. Feature-level metadata is not provided in the US Topo product; there is no link
              between a line on the map and the source of that specific trail. Notes on data sources follow --------- For the 11 National Scenic
              Trails (NST): Ice Age National Scenic Trail: data provided by the volunteer organization Ice Age Trail Alliance,
              http://www.iceagetrail.org, in cooperation with National Park Service and Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources. - Pacific Crest
              National Scenic Trail: unpublished data provided by US Forest Service - Appalachian National Scenic Trail: data published by the
              Appalachian Trial Conservancy, http://appalachiantrail.org/about-the-trail/mapping-gis-data, in cooperation with National Park Service -
              North Country National Scenic Trail: unpublished dataset provided by National Park Service - Arizona National Scenic Trail: data from
              AZGEO Clearinghouse, https://azgeo.az.gov/azgeo/, in cooperation with U.S. Forest Service - Pacific Northwest National Scenic Trail:
              unpublished data provided by US Forest Service - Natchez Trace National Scenic Trail: unpublished dataset provided by National Park
              Service --------- For other trail types and sources: US Fish and Wildlife Service lands: the USFWS Hiking Trails Inventory is
              administered by the US Department of Transportation Federal Highway Administration, and Pacific Western Technologies, LTD. The purpose
              of the dataset is to create a baseline inventory of all non-motorized trails on US Fish and Wildlife Service Stations. - US Forest
              Service lands: trails within National Forests are from unpublished data provided by USFS. These data are developed from sources of
              differing accuracy. US Topo does not portray access and travel management information indicating which trails are managed for or open to
              specific modes of travel (motorized/non-motorized) or associated seasons of use. USFS trails (other than selected NSTs described above)
              are currently shown on US Topo only in Colorado. - The International Mountain Bicycling Association, IMBA, shares their bicycle trails
              data with USGS as part of an ongoing partnership. IMBA-collected trails are generally not shown inside delineated Federal lands (e.g.,
              National Forests) on US Topo maps.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.nps.gov/ncrc/programs/nts/nts_trails.html</onlink>
            <onlink>http://www.pnts.org</onlink>
            <onlink>http://www.fws.gov/gis/data/national/</onlink>
            <onlink>https://www.imba.com/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2006</begdate>
              <enddate>2014</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Recreational Trails</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Trail centerline</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Census Bureau, Geography Division</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Transportation, Census Roads</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>Dataset source is Census Bureau MAF/TIGER database extracts in the form of TIGER/Line Shapefiles. The TIGER/Line shapefiles and
              related database files are an extract of selected geographic and cartographic information from the U.S. Census Bureau's Master Address
              File/Topologically Integrated Geographic Encoding and Referencing (MAF/TIGER) Database (MTDB). The MTDB represents a seamless national
              file with no overlaps or gaps between parts, however, each TIGER/Line shapefile is designed to stand alone as an independent dataset, or
              they can be combined to cover the entire nation. The U.S. Geological Survey filters Census roads to remove short road segments which are
              less than 500 feet in length, are not named and are classified as local roads. The USGS National Transportation Dataset functional road
              classification system is applied to the Census datasets. The original TIGER/Line Shapefile products are not copyrighted however
              TIGER/Line and Census TIGER are registered trademarks of the U.S. Census Bureau. The horizontal spatial accuracy information present in
              the TIGER/Line shapefiles is provided for the purposes of statistical analysis and census operations only and the data may not be
              suitable for high-precision measurement applications. Full metadata for TIGER/Line shapefiles is available from U.S. Census
              Bureau</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.census.gov/geo/maps-data/data/tiger.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2013</begdate>
              <enddate>2014</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Roads - Census</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Road centerlines, route numbers, road classification, street names</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Alaska Railroad Corporation</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Transportation, Railroads</title>
            <geoform>Vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>This record applies to Alaska data only. Railroad data is provided by the Alaska Railroad Corporation, and may not include other
              owner's rail features. Unpublished data provided directly to USGS. Current as of 2012. For more information, contact Alaska Railroad
              Corporation, 327 W. Ship Creek Ave., Anchorage, AK. 99501, phone 907-265-3100, or emailgrunwaldm@akrrr.com</othercit>
            <onlink />
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>25000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2012</begdate>
              <enddate>2012</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Railroads - Alaska Railroad Corporation</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Main track centerlines</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Alaska Department of Transportation</origin>
            <pubdate>20180210</pubdate>
            <title>Transportation, public domain roads</title>
            <geoform>Vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>This record applies to Alaska data only. Roads gathered from various state and local sources, integrated by the Alaska
              Department of Transportation (ADOT) and provided to USGS for use in USGS map products. This specific road dataset is unpublished, but
              earlier versions are published on the ADOT web site.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.dot.state.ak.us/stwdplng/mapping/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>25000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>2013</begdate>
              <enddate>2013</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Roads - Alaska Department of Transportation</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Road centerlines, road classification, street names</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>The data for this product are created as follows. All geospatial content is taken from national geospatial databases under the
          stewardship of USGS data programs. The NAIP imagery is provided by a seamless tile service that delivers image data at the resolution and
          quality of the source imagery. The raster and vector data, including grids and collar information, are processed using ESRI ArcGIS software
          and exported. Map formatting is performed using a custom application, which includes post-processing to embed the metadata XML
          document.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20180210</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>Public Land Survey System</indspref>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
      </sdtsterm>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>Void polygon composed of rings</sdtstype>
      </sdtsterm>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>Complete chain</sdtstype>
      </sdtsterm>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>Complete chain</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>1012</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <geograph>
        <latres>0.00001</latres>
        <longres>0.00001</longres>
        <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
      </geograph>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.2572221</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Geospatial Technical Operations Center</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1400 Independence Road</address>
          <city>Rolla</city>
          <state>MO</state>
          <postal>65401</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Box 25046 Denver Federal Center</address>
          <city>Lakewood</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-ASK-USGS (1-888-275-8747)</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>http://www.usgs.gov/ask/</cntemail>
        <hours>Monday through Friday 8:00 AM to 4:00 PM</hours>
        <cntinst>Metadata information can also be obtained through online services using The National Map Viewer, at http://nationalmap.usgs.gov or
          EarthExplorer, at http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov or Ask USGS at http://www.usgs.gov/ask.</cntinst>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
    <distliab>No liability for content or accuracy is presumed by USGS for data.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>FileGDB</formname>
          <formvern>10.1</formvern>
          <formcont>Spatial objects with unique identifiers and coordinate data.</formcont>
          <filedec>No compression applied</filedec>
          <transize>4191945</transize>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>ftp://rockyftp.cr.usgs.gov/vdelivery/Datasets/Staged/TopoMapVector/SD/Shape/VECTOR_Howard_SD_7_5_Min_Shape.zip</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20180210</metd>
    <metrd>20180210</metrd>
    <metfrd>20190210</metfrd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Geospatial Technical Operations Center</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1400 Independence Road</address>
          <city>Rolla</city>
          <state>MO</state>
          <postal>65401</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Box 25046 Denver Federal Center</address>
          <city>Lakewood</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-ASK-USGS (1-888-275-8747)</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>http://www.usgs.gov/ask/</cntemail>
        <hours>Monday through Friday 8:00 AM to 4:00 PM</hours>
        <cntinst>Metadata information can also be obtained through online services using The National Map Viewer, at http://nationalmap.usgs.gov or
          EarthExplorer, at http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov or Ask USGS at http://www.usgs.gov/ask.</cntinst>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>