<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "http://thor-f5.er.usgs.gov/ngtoc/metadata/fgdc-std-001-1998.dtd"[]>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, National Geospatial Program</origin>
        <pubdate>20180211</pubdate>
        <title>USGS NED 1/3 arc-second Contours for Watertown W, South Dakota 20180211 1 X 1 degree Shapefile</title>
        <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>ftp://rockyftp.cr.usgs.gov/vdelivery/Datasets/Staged/Elev/Shape/ELEV_Watertown_W_SD_1X1_Shape.zip</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>These vector contour lines are derived from the 3D Elevation Program using automated and semi-automated processes. They were
				created to support 1:24,000-scale topographic map products, but are also published in this GIS vector format. Contour intervals are
				assigned by 7.5-minute quadrangle, so this vector dataset is not visually seamless across quadrangle boundaries. The vector lines have
				elevation attributes (in feet above mean sea level on NAVD88), but this dataset does not carry line symbols or annotation.</abstract>
      <purpose>This dataset represents variant packaging of USGS elevation data. The primary USGS elevation products are gridded elevation
				points; contours are derived from these data for standard contour maps, and these contour data are also published as GIS vectors.
				Contours are typically a means of representing elevations for human visualization on maps, and are never more accurate than the
				gridded elevation data they are derived from.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20120403</begdate>
          <enddate>20150309</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>publication date</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Irregular</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-97.9999999999999</westbc>
        <eastbc>-96.9999999999999</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.0000000000001</northbc>
        <southbc>44.0000000000001</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>elevation</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Geospatial Platform</themekt>
        <themekey>ngda</themekey>
        <themekey>Elevation Terrestrial</themekey>
        <themekey>National Elevation Dataset (NED) 1/3 arc-second - Contours</themekey>
        <themekey>1 x 1 degree</themekey>
        <themekey>Shapefile</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>US</placekey>
        <placekey>United States</placekey>
        <placekey>SD</placekey>
        <placekey>South Dakota</placekey>
        <placekey>MinerCounty</placekey>
        <placekey>SanbornCounty</placekey>
        <placekey>CodingtonCounty</placekey>
        <placekey>LakeCounty</placekey>
        <placekey>BrookingsCounty</placekey>
        <placekey>SpinkCounty</placekey>
        <placekey>HamlinCounty</placekey>
        <placekey>KingsburyCounty</placekey>
        <placekey>BeadleCounty</placekey>
        <placekey>ClarkCounty</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None. However, users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since this data set was collected and that some parts
			of this data may no longer represent actual surface conditions. Users should not use this data for critical applications without a full
			awareness of its limitations. Acknowledgment of the U.S. Geological Survey would be appreciated for products derived from these
			data.</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>ftp://rockyftp.cr.usgs.gov/vdelivery/Datasets/Staged/Elev/Shape/ELEV_Watertown_W_SD_1X1_Shape.jpg</browsen>
      <browsed>Thumbnail JPG image</browsed>
      <browset>JPEG</browset>
    </browse>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Lines of constant elevation are derived from the USGS 3D Elevation Program using automated processes. The contours are designed
				for visual clarity at 1:24,000 scale and a quadrangle-specific contour interval.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>The National Elevation Dataset is seamless. Although the data accuracy varies, the data generally have high enough resolution and
			accuracy to support consistent and accurate contours at 1:24,000 scale.</logic>
    <complete>The National Elevation Dataset is national in scope, with complete coverage of the conterminous 48 states, Hawaii, the US Virgin
			Islands and Puerto Rico. There is partial coverage for Alaska.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Contours do not have well-defined position, so National Map Accuracy Standards (NMAS) for horizontal accuracy do not apply.
					Contour positions are, on average, accurate to within one-half contour interval</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>The most recently published figure of overall absolute vertical accuracy of the 3DEP within the conterminous US, expressed
					as the root mean square error (RMSE) of 25,310 reference points is 1.55 meters. However, the vertical accuracy actually varies
					significantly across the US because of differences in source quality, terrain relief, land cover, and other factors. Details of
					this analysis are published in "Accuracy Assessment of the U.S. Geological Survey National Elevation Dataset, and Comparison
					with Other Large-Area Elevation Dataset-SRTM and ASTER: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 2014-1008,"
					http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2014/1008/. </vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, National Geospatial Technical Operations Center - National Elevation Dataset is a component of
							a comprehensive base geospatial data model.</origin>
            <pubdate>20180211</pubdate>
            <title>Hypsography</title>
            <geoform>Vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>This contour featureclass was generated from the 1/3 arc-second version of the 3D Elevation Program. The intended
							viewing scale for these features is 1:24,000. The contours are derived from a filtered elevation raster to achieve
							smoother arcs. In some areas, the 3DEP data may be modified by the National Hydrography Dataset (NHD) flow lines and water
							bodies to facilitate improved integration between the hypsography and hydrography on USGS map products. These contours
							were generated primarily for use as a layer in GeoPDFs created in the digital mapping program. The raster data source of
							contours is the 3D Elevation Program 1/3 arc-second layer. Secondary datasets include the high resolution flow lines,
							water bodies, and areas from the National Hydrography Dataset (NHD). The NHD layers are used in hydro-enforcement of the
							DEM prior to contour generation. The goals of the hydro-enforcement are to prevent contour lines from extending over the
							surface of water bodies and to align the contour reentrants with the NHD single- line streams. The 3DEP raster cells are
							converted to points. Those points, along with the NHD flow lines are input into an interpolation tool to create a new
							surface. The NHD water bodies and areas are preprocessed to attach the minimum and maximum elevation to each polygon. From
							these precalculated values, an appropriate value is calculated by which to raise the elevation cells under the NHD
							polygons. The NHD polygons are then converted into rasters, which in turn will be used to generate a mosaic that includes
							the new raster surface. The mosaic is filtered to provide smoother contour lines. Contours are generated and depression
							and index contours are identified. There is no guarantee or warranty concerning the accuracy of the data. Users should be
							aware that temporal changes may have occurred since these data were collected and generated and that some parts of these
							data may no longer represent actual surface conditions. Hydro-enforcement and generalization can also significantly alter
							the spatial characteristics of the contours. Users should not use these data for critical applications without a full
							awareness of its limitations.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://Hs.gov/</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate />
              <enddate />
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Hypsography</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Contours</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Contour lines are created from USGS gridded elevation data, using automated and semi-automated processes, followed by
					limited visual inspection to verify quality, and occasionally editing to improve contour readability and registration with water
					features in the National Hydrography Dataset. Software is ArcGIS based, with some USGS customization.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20180211</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <geograph>
        <latres>0.00001</latres>
        <longres>0.00001</longres>
        <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
      </geograph>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.2572221</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Geospatial Technical Operations Center</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1400 Independence Road</address>
          <city>Rolla</city>
          <state>MO</state>
          <postal>65401</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Box 25046 Denver Federal Center</address>
          <city>Lakewood</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-ASK-USGS (1-888-275-8747)</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>http://www.usgs.gov/ask/</cntemail>
        <hours>Monday through Friday 8:00 AM to 4:00 PM</hours>
        <cntinst>Metadata information can also be obtained through online services using The National Map Viewer, at
					http://nationalmap.usgs.gov or EarthExplorer, at http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov or Ask USGS at http://www.usgs.gov/ask.</cntinst>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
    <distliab>No liability for content or accuracy is presumed by USGS for data.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>FileGDB</formname>
          <formvern>10.1</formvern>
          <formcont>Spatial objects with unique identifiers and coordinate data.</formcont>
          <filedec>No compression applied</filedec>
          <transize>104297701</transize>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>ftp://rockyftp.cr.usgs.gov/vdelivery/Datasets/Staged/Elev/Shape/ELEV_Watertown_W_SD_1X1_Shape.zip</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20180211</metd>
    <metrd>20180211</metrd>
    <metfrd>20190211</metfrd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Geospatial Technical Operations Center</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1400 Independence Road</address>
          <city>Rolla</city>
          <state>MO</state>
          <postal>65401</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Box 25046 Denver Federal Center</address>
          <city>Lakewood</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-ASK-USGS (1-888-275-8747)</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>http://www.usgs.gov/ask/</cntemail>
        <hours>Monday through Friday 8:00 AM to 4:00 PM</hours>
        <cntinst>Metadata information can also be obtained through online services using The National Map Viewer, at
					http://nationalmap.usgs.gov or EarthExplorer, at http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov or Ask USGS at http://www.usgs.gov/ask.</cntinst>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>